[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this practice, if you want any results from it, if you want to practice, you have to be able to face your dukkha and not cover it up with some... something.
[SPEAKER_00]: With some management, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to give up things that you use to cover up your dukkha, so that you can face it, so that you can overcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And these are, what I would say is, those are the attachments in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Attachments are the cover-ups that make you feel better in regard to your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: The attachments offer a sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Familiarity, comfort, which all revolves around, kind of, you're finding refuge in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, well, that's why, like, the practice is, you know, people might... a person hears this and they might think, right, so I'll just give everything up overnight, sell my house, abandon the family, do everything that, like, all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, that still will not necessarily free you from being attached to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead, you could just take on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you're going to feel the attachments basically being... the attaching aspect of attachments being undermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you are undermining now your own safety in a much more fundamental sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not letting the senses control your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not letting the mind govern your choices and behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead, you're imposing certain limits, and now the mind will resist it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you're going to start seeing why you had all the attachments the way you did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why you were finding comfort, because you had access, basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: To things, they were pacifying the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were keeping the mind away from turning against you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were sort of distracting it, keeping it occupied, so it was bearable, pleasant, agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could be giving everything up, but if you're not actually undermining that wilderness of your mind, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: your own desires,
[SPEAKER_01]: No difference will be made.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why asceticism is equally ignoble as sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your desires, underneath it all, remain unaffected, unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of giving everything up overnight, give up sensual cravings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start by reducing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start by reducing engagement with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are actually undermining the framework of attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Removing that basis
[SPEAKER_01]: That serves as a safety to you, as a refuge, because it's not truly safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there were like many lay people in the suttas who would have, who were like anāgāmīs, who were freed from sensuality, let alone who had the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the path is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to take on the behavior that will undermine the relentless, unchecked desire in your mind, that basically is how these attachments are established, perpetuated, reinforced.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you wouldn't be... or if you were attached to your family, say for example, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: The family just turns against you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just starts making your life unbearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your own relatives, your own people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no desire anymore to stay there, because there is no more sense of safety there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a threat now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will leave it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't have a problem abandoning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if some part of you, ideologically, still thinks, but it's, you know, it's my family.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practically, you'll be doing it out of a sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you can't get what you want, if what you want is being taken away, if all those things are constantly repeated, your attachment will vanish.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the threat of those things is revealed, dissatisfaction, you will not want them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where the practice really is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you take on the precepts and some basic sensory strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, that's the, like, necessary first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not really about these grand gestures of giving things up and abandoning it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about bringing up those perceptions of non-ownership, of non-control, of how everything that's dear to you will be and is already otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: How it could change?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a real... that possibility is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't wait for it to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it could change means... implies it's within the domain of change, which means it's not in my control, even if it's the way I want it to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those are the things that will really make people anxious and afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, as I said before, it's not the worst type of pain you can go through.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can take all sorts of factually extreme pains, if they have a desire to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they have a good reason to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Austere practices, hunger strikes, starvation, like... choosing death, basically, out of conviction, out of desire, out of zeal, out of inspiration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like factually unbearable experience, people would take on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nobody
[SPEAKER_01]: would have a desire to subtly, on that right level, undermine their own desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: To say no to sensuality, to bring up these doubtful states, doubtful states of mind that are besetting you, and choose not to give in, or try to get rid of them, or act out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that subtle anxiety, unease, when you contemplate dukkha and so on, in and of itself, it's not unbearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just particularly unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nobody will accidentally choose to stay, repeatedly, for as long as it's necessary, with that particular type of displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you just... Well, first, it doesn't feel like much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feels like you need to do more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you want to basically, like, double down in these efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of cutting the ties and all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: While in reality, all you need to do is just contain your senses and leave everything else as it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just take on the virtue in terms of, obviously, stop the unwholesome behavior that proliferates those desires and then do the same on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And initially, it's gonna be a particular type of confinement felt and particular type of uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the worst one, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because it's subtle, it's because it's ambiguous, it's because it's not so palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not palpable like the pleasures of the senses, and it's not palpable like the pains of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of neither here nor there, and that drives people insane.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nobody will choose to willingly stay with that particular layer of
[SPEAKER_01]: Not giving in to trying to overly think and resolve this doubt about what should I do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not giving in and trying to resolve this anxiety of, oh, things could be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody would protect that state of mind, because it doesn't feel right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't feel, like, good.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the khandha of the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know what's good, you don't know what's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: From a point of view of Putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to abandon attachments, just stay... Well, as the Sutta says, actually, the foremost in outsider's view is that view that... How is it formulated?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I might have to paraphrase it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be, it won't be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could have not been, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that which is, it's not for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I... it's not in my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you... somebody adheres to that view, as the sutta says, even without anything else, they would have removed a lot of obstructions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means they would be on the... on the verge of sotāpati, just with... with probably some... like an external utterance, in terms of fixing a few things, how to attend to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is how you abandon attachments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by killing yourself, destroying your house, abandoning this... By staying in the state of recognition, a certain perspective, that things that have arisen, did not arise for you, it's just circumstantially they are so, and things that will arise, or would have arisen, won't be for you either.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible, basically, to cross in the domain of ownership in regard to things that are dearest to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's true in regard to things that are not dear to you, but the contemplation has to be about things that are dear to you, not about random stones and trees and stuff that you don't care about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it has to be about stuff that's dear to me, stuff that I'm finding safety in, that I'm using basically to cover up that anxiety of non-control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, keep the precept until that's revealed and then protect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Endure it, how I say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, don't try to overly psychologize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's because of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant why it is so.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is relevant is that you are resisting it internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind doesn't want to be with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind will rather
[SPEAKER_01]: Take on great austerities and great determinations or commit to sensuality, then stay in that, like, ambiguous, neither here nor there, mildly anxious kind of undertone of uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the neutral feeling the Buddha talked about.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it's not understood, it will be felt like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be felt unpleasant, it will be felt uncomfortable, but it isn't so.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only because you're not understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only because you're looking past it, which is why you're resisting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Frequently recollect.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there's the literal, like the frequent recollection that we were talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of them was everything that's dear to me,
[SPEAKER_01]: will be and is otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, frequently recollecting that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monks as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if this thing is taken away?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, how do I deal with that?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's like, how do I remain unmoved in regard to those perceptions?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no dealing with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no preventing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: One way or the other, it's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, either I refuse to think about it, and then wait until it happens, and then I'll just sort of bear it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I will think about it and endure that kind of certain dissonance of my feeling, because it just doesn't feel right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, that's exactly why it doesn't feel right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the framework you're holding, wrongly assumed, is the framework of ownership and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is discrepant with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which one do you choose then?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, if you have right instruction and faith in the right instruction, you would stick to this until that framework, wrong framework, wrongly assumed framework, is dissolved.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you won't feel wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will feel the most natural thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which used to be anxiety, now it's a quite a liberating, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Weightless.
[SPEAKER_01]: No burden involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're untouched.